<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>matt gray</title>
    <description>Internet residence of Matt Gray. Clarifying for ambiguity, this Matt Gray develops software, trains for gymnastics, and is a lover of music.
</description>
    <link>http://mattgray.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://mattgray.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 11:29:42 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 11:29:42 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>On productivity and pursuing diverse long-term goals</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The Problem:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my self-improvement currently comes from physical activities. Side-projects and learning outside of school used to be important but it has fallen by the wayside. I would like to find more of a balance between all kinds of self-improvement and meaningful relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;details&quot;&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously pursuing physical training has changed my life for the better in a great number of ways - self-confidence, how I feel on a daily basis, I could list many different things. It has become a consistent hobby I can work towards and further my abilities with and that’s so rewarding in its own right even looking past what it does for the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, where time and energy has been invested in my schooling and physical activities, it has been taken from other avenues of self-improvement. Five years ago, I couldn’t keep myself out of picking up side projects, reading another book, or learning another programming language. While I have worked on things sporadically and read a book here or there, I feel like a different person in terms of improving my knowledge in other areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I have become so aware of this is that in the online fitness community, many people push the improvement of the mind along with the body. While this is a great thing, sometimes it becomes daunting to manage relaxation, personal relationships, fitness, school/work, sleep, and all other activities under the rainbow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where am I going with this? I’m not really sure. Mindfulness of how I would like to change my habits is a good first step. Sometimes I’m doubtful of being able to improve productivity on learning outside of school while I’m also working on my actual studies and finding time to relax among all of that, but I also realize how much time I waste on what I think of as &lt;strong&gt;meaningless relaxation&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m not even referring to video games or movies, but social media for the most part. Sites with endless feeds have some value to them when looking for something in particular, but going on them out of boredom has been one of the most toxic habits I’ve gotten into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The Solution?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve subscribed to minimalist ideals since coming to college and they genuinely have made a difference in my life. One important thing I have applied minimalism to is the minimalism of choice. If I don’t have the choice to engage in a bad habit (example: you can’t browse instagram (easily) if you delete the app), thinking about doing it does no good. The issue comes in when I do get value out of these sites - some conversations I have had on reddit or instagram have been invaluable for broadening my horizons. So what do I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, being mindful of the problem and the solution is a big help. Just asking myself what I’m getting out of something whenever I do it is helpful. Writing about it is good as well, hence this post. Actionable-item-wise, here’s what I’m going to do going forward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hide time-wasting apps from my phone homescreen. Not seeing them is a small difference, but it definitely helps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deleting apps that I truly get no benefit from (I define benefit as something that I’ll remember long-term, not just nod or chuckle at, or be able to apply to my life).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsubscribing from subreddits/pages that I truly get no benefit from.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turning off my phone when I am working, so that I can work in more quality discrete blocks of time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relax with things I enjoy more and will remember: shows I have wanted to see, playing video games with friends, reading fun books, spending time with people close to me without meaningless distractions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I implement some of those ideas, I’ll have more time to evaluate my ability to work on side-projects and learning. I’ve noticed trying to take too big of a jump (wasting time -&amp;gt; making productive use of time) can be difficult and easy to fail at. I’m going to try making a smaller jump from wasting time with meaningless relaxation, to condensing my work time and making my relaxation more quality. Then the mental energy should be higher and I should be able to more easily invest it in more productive ventures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/thoughts/2018/04/10/on-productivity-and-pursuing-goals.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/thoughts/2018/04/10/on-productivity-and-pursuing-goals.html</guid>
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Overcoming Poor Posture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;booktitle&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://systematicposture.com&quot;&gt;Overcoming Poor Posture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by Steven Low and Jarlo Ilano - This title has been sitting on my desk for too long. I just finished reading through it (skimming some of the exercise sections, which are a great use for later reference, because I don't have the ability to get on the floor of the plane I'm on and try them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won't try and summarize in great detail what the book is about (great detail isn't even necessary because the book clocks in at about 120 pages including the posture/mobility program appendix), that should be mostly obvious from the title anyways. Steven and Jarlo do a great job at succintly summarizing many concepts about posture and related areas and not overanalyzing details that aren't important to the layman &lt;em&gt;simply looking to improve their posture&lt;/em&gt;. Following a brief look at these concepts, they talk about basic exercises to improve posture and work mobility over the entire body. After looking at exercises a nod is given to forming habits before discussing programming and finally some sample routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite part about the book, and this is evident in the rest of Steven's writing and philosophies (I'm not as familiar with Jarlo, although I would like to look more into his work after reading this), is how realistic he is to how most people tackle change, especially physical change. They acknowledge that nothing is overnight and that the work written about in this book should be done in a way that works with the reader. The book is not dogmatic about anything being done a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I'd just like to conclude by saying that this is a great book (especially when used as a reference) and if you care about posture or mobility, you should add it to your collection. Reading it through only took two hours on a plane ride and going forward I'll be able to jump in to the appendix and utilize the exercises I thought might be notable for me. Thanks for reading this little review, I hope you enjoyed it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/books/2018/03/08/overcoming-poor-posture.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/books/2018/03/08/overcoming-poor-posture.html</guid>
        
        <category>books</category>
        
        <category>fitness</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weighted Bodyweight: Programming</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Originally posted on February 24th, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update February 27th, 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For beginner/intermediate/advanced benchmarks, I &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/19l4tVfdTJLheLMwZBYqcw1oeEBPRh8mxngqrCz2YnVg/edit#gid=2032740838&quot;&gt;the overcoming gravity progression charts&lt;/a&gt; found at that link (google sheet). If that link becomes out-dated for some reason, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/overcominggravity&quot;&gt;/r/overcominggravity&lt;/a&gt; and you should be able to find the link on there in the side-bar or by asking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/bodyweightfitness/comments/806f83/writeup_a_way_to_program_weighted_chinsdips_for/&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a reddit/bodyweightfitness thread I posted for this write-up and there was some good discussion in the comments. I’ll follow up on some points mentioned here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post is written assuming a full-body routine with 3x per week frequency. You could also do it with some other kind of split, but that’s outside the scope of this post. A 3x per week full-body routine is what I’m recommending around. You’d need to add skill work, horizontal plane movements, leg movements, accessory work, and mobility to this routine to make it complete. **IF you can only do 2x/week, I recommend starting with the beginner progression until you can reach an intermediate stage, and then doing light/heavy with potentially a bit more volume to make up for the lack of a third session during the week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rest should be what you need, I think a good start is 90s between sets of dips and chins (or other strength pairs). Take more if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back-off sets are something you should figure out to be appropriate over time. If you want an objective measurement, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;((added weight + bodyweight) * .9) - bodyweight&lt;/code&gt; can work, but it may not be perfect (or even work with very light amounts of weight added). I recommend back-off sets because I think working up to a top (&lt;strong&gt;top does not equate to failure&lt;/strong&gt;) set in the range you’re working in that day and then backing-off is a good way to regulate how hard you’re pushing yourself. You could just do sets across, but similar to the point on the split itself, these are my recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post &lt;strong&gt;is not about building up bodyweight reps of pull-ups and dips&lt;/strong&gt;. There are a lot of resources on that topic that are different and people find their way through that easily enough over time (some longer than others). I’m trying to put into words my own method for auto-regulation and progression of weighted pull-ups and dips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of various protocols out there for starting to add weight. Some of them are good, some of them aren’t. Most work, but a lot are inefficient. In three years of bodyweight training, about 2 of which are with this method (after building up just bodyweight reps), I went from no dips or chin-ups (starting from 4 years ago), to a +160lb chin-up and +180lb dip at 200lbs bodyweight (currently maintaining at +135lbs for 4 on dips and for 2 on chin-ups).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous-notes&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t say which exercise to do in the templates, &lt;strong&gt;you should be doing dips and chins paired together.&lt;/strong&gt; That means: do a set of chins or dips, rest about 90s, and do the other exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notation used for sets and reps is as follows: &lt;strong&gt;SETSxREPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When rep ranges are given, you usually want to start with something you know you can do on the lower end of the range and work up in reps over your time training. So if the rep range is 10-20, start with a set of 10ish and over your time training progress that working set up to the high teens and eventually 20 repetitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, I will refer to weighted pull-ups or weighted chin-ups as chins. If you want to do supinated/under-grip, neutral/hammer-grip (I prefer this one because it feels best on the shoulders and elbows), or pronated/over-grip, then that’s up to you. The difference is relatively minimal. I don’t like pronated/pull-ups because that grip can make it be difficult to define a stopping-point (chin above? chest-to-bar?) whereas supinated/neutral you pull until your arm is fully flexed and that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually only perform pull-ups (pronated) for bodyweight reps. That’s my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, training weighted chins and dips is rough. Take care of yourself, eat quality food, sleep well, stay hydrated, and if your joints feel funky, back-off the intensity a bit. You want to be in this for the long-run, not a short sprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you should be uninjured and physically able to train. Second, I’m not a certified trainer or anything like that,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to put any hard prerequisites down, just some that I would suggest (to prevent injury, and obviously to build necessary strength). All of these prerequisites should be able to be completed without any pain (for example, sternum pain when performing dips). I’m not a physiotherapist, get your own injuries sorted out before training something that could worsen them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building up basic push/pull strength with 15-20 push-ups and horizontal rows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having the shoulder mobility to do a parallel dip without pain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conditioning yourself for weighted chins and dips with 10-15 chins/dips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once these are completed (lower end is what I would say is a minimum, higher end will just mean you’re even more prepared). I wish it was needless to say, but these all require &lt;strong&gt;good form:&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For dips, use a full range of motion (&lt;em&gt;at the top:&lt;/em&gt; arms fully extended/locked-out, shoulders depressed, &lt;em&gt;at the bottom:&lt;/em&gt; upper arm parallel to the ground (for depth, go deeper only if you have the mobility), forearm should remain relatively vertical).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For chins, use a full range of motion (&lt;em&gt;at the bottom:&lt;/em&gt; shoulders relaxed, &lt;em&gt;at the top:&lt;/em&gt; arm fully flexed (if neutral/supinated) or chin clearly over (if pronated)).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think there are other form guidelines to adhere to, feel free to comment them below or follow them yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;programming&quot;&gt;Programming&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, these are programming &lt;em&gt;suggestions&lt;/em&gt; I have found to work well. I’ll break it up into three stages (beginner/intermediate/advanced) for progression because athletes at different stages progress at different rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One large factor in regards to where you start with progression is your bodyweight and gender as well as how well you can recover (influenced by diet/caloric surplus or deficit, genetics, etc). I started as a tall, skinny, lean male with a lot of room to put on muscle mass, I was also eating and sleeping really well, and along with the fact that I have decent athletic genetics (looking at what family members have done in the past), I was in a good position to progress somewhat quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re on the opposite side of the spectrum and struggle to progress upper body strength, then you may not be able to start in the beginner stage because progressing that fast is just not something you’re able to do. Don’t sweat it! Everyone is different, take what you can do and own it :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beginner&quot;&gt;Beginner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re new to weighting your chins/dips, you have taken a break from training them for a while, or you have a decent base and can recover adequately, then you may respond well to linear progression. Having a larger base of bodyweight reps will help a lot. Training 2-3x a week at this stage is good, 3x a week is the best (from personal experience with myself and others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a general template which I will explain below (assuming working out on Monday/Wednesday/Friday). You can do a horizontal push and pull (push-ups/bench and rows) each day along with legs on whichever days you want (this template is geared primarily towards weighted chins and dips):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every Week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M: 3x5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;W: 3x5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;F: 3x5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Keep it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression and Key Ideas:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 2.5lbs from last session to each exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can’t progress for a session (complete 3x5), then try repeating the same weight during the next session and add an extra set. If a trend continues (for a week or so) where you can’t progress, then maybe take a deload week and consider switching to an intermediate template if the progression doesn’t feel sustainable going forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you’ll notice, each work-out is the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; except for increasing weights. That’s linear progression. There are a few ways to modify this and push yourself further if desired. One way to change up this routine to make it exciting is to make your last set you do an AMRAP (as many reps as possible, I would write that as 3x5+ where the last set is minimum 5, maximum as much as possible) so you can see just how many reps you can get with that weight. If you get 10 reps on the AMRAP set, you could even add 5lbs the next workout instead of 2.5lbs. I would &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommend stopping on that set with 1 rep left in the tank. Beginners can push themselves more and still recover, but not going to &lt;em&gt;complete&lt;/em&gt; failure is desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of progression can last anywhere from not at all to a couple of months. You’re adding 7.5lbs a week, this obviously can’t continue forever. A good &lt;strong&gt;stopping point&lt;/strong&gt; is when you can’t progress for a week, as mentioned above in the template itself. Consider taking a deload (mentioned below) and trying another 3-4 week cycle of this beginner progression or switching to an intermediate routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I progressed from 20 bodyweight chin reps to +70lbs for 3x5 in about 3-4 months. As I said above, I started from a good position, so YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intermediate&quot;&gt;Intermediate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get to an intermediate stage (usually after a few months to a year of steady training, including starting from just bodyweight without weight) and you can’t recover to linearly progress with a beginner routine, then, what do you know, it’s time for an intermediate routine. This routine is made for intermediates by adding a form of &lt;strong&gt;periodization&lt;/strong&gt; where the trainee alternates between a light day and heavy day. If you’re unfamiliar with it, give it a google. Learning more is always helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As said above, I prefer to do periodize for the intermediate stage by alternating between light and heavy days. For chins and dips, &lt;em&gt;light would correspond to 8+ reps accumulating around 30-45 reps across your sets&lt;/em&gt; (the lower end of that range, 8, should only be used if it’s not to failure, higher reps are to build volume and accumulate work/fatigue, not to kill your body with intensity). &lt;em&gt;Heavy days would correspond to 3-8 repetitions accumulating 15-25 reps across your sets&lt;/em&gt; (again, trying not to fail, especially at the lower ends of the rep range, failure exhausts the body and nervous system). A training template might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 1:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M: Light - Work up to a top-set of 8-12, then either drop the weight (or drop the reps if not weighted, this is a light day) and try and hit 2-3 back-off sets to hit the rep goal with lower weight/reps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;W: Heavy - Work up to a top-set of 3-5, then hit 3-4 back-off sets with lower weight to hit the rep goal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;F: Light - Work up to a top-set of 8-15, then either drop the weight (or drop the reps if not weighted, this is a light day) and try and hit 2-3 back-off sets to hit the rep goal with lower weight/reps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 2:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M: Heavy - Work up to a top-set of 3-5, then hit 3-4 back-off sets with lower weight to hit the rep goal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;W: Light - Work up to a top-set of 8-15, then either drop the weight (or drop the reps if not weighted, this is a light day) and try and hit 2-3 back-off sets to hit the rep goal with lower weight/reps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;F: Heavy - Work up to a top-set of 3-5, then hit 3-4 back-off sets with lower weight to hit the rep goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression and Key Ideas:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Once you get out of beginner stage&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s much harder to push yourself to the limit every session. You NEED to keep some gas left in the tank, for lack of a better phrase, during your working sets. You should try to have at least 1 if not 2 reps left in the tank on top sets and have 2-4 reps left in the tank on back-off sets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can’t progress reps or weight from one light or one heavy session to the next session of the same, then try and match the same reps as last session and add one back-off set with the same reps (maybe two if you can’t match reps) and also considering deloading if you feel really gassed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can’t progress for a week, then take a deload week. This is usually between every 4 and every 6 weeks depending on one’s recovery capacity. Only consider switching to an advanced template if the progression doesn’t feel sustainable for two to three cycles in a row. The intermediate stage lasts longer than beginner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advanced&quot;&gt;Advanced&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advanced stage, depending on how fast you progress, is usually reached after a few years of steady training, maybe sooner or later depending on the person. At this point you’re lifting some heavy weights and you’ll usually need to do a lot more work to get just a little bit further. At this point, you should have an idea about how you respond to training stimulus, so maybe the template I’m going to list will work for you, maybe it won’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key idea here is daily undulating periodization, which I wrote about a bit &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgray.net/fitness/2017/07/27/intermediate-advanced-gymnastics-strength.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It takes the light/heavy periodization one step further and adds a medium day so you do work each week in every rep range: endurance, strength, and power. Some people like 8-12/5-8/3-5 for light/medium/heavy respectively. I’ve seen better results personally working in the 10-20/6-10/3-6 range. That higher repetition day really reenforces the movement pattern you’re working on (that’s anecdotal/personal training experience) and gives a break from hammering away at heavy and intense exercise. Here’s the template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M: Light - Work up to a top weighted set for between 10 and 20 reps. Hit some back-off sets to accumulate around 50 reps of total volume.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;W: Medium - Work up to a top weighted set for between 5 and 10 reps. Hit some back-off sets to accumulate around 35-40 reps of total volume.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;F: Heavy - Work up to a top weighted set for between 3 and 5 reps. Hit some back-off sets to accumulate around 25-30 reps of total volume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression and Key Ideas:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This stage is a lot more loose in regards to how you program and how it needs to be individualized. The key idea is to to just keep the weights and reps trend going up over time. Build volume each week by adding weight to your top sets when you can, or if your top set struggles to go up, adding to your back-off sets with more weight and more repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You will most likely need some well-chosen accessory exercises (curls, face-pulls, etc) to keep your body balanced and injury-free at this stage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You should have an idea about how often you need to deload by this stage. When your progress starts stagnating it’s definitely time for a deload and to keep an eye on your recovery methods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At this stage, if you start stagnating across multiple mesocycles (multiple week blocks), consider switching up your programming style or even your goals for a while. Build up your horizontal pushing and pulling strength some more with planche and front lever. Work some accessories more to shore up your weak points. It’s all about finding the missing piece to the puzzle at this point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deloading---a-side-note&quot;&gt;Deloading - a side note.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried multiple styles of deloads at different points in my training, here’s some of them just for some ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When I’m mentally and physically exhausted, sometimes I just need a day or two away from my normal training cycle to focus on other things in life, maybe get a massage, work some mobility, take some more walks, and reflect on my training. When this happens I’ll just make sure to move around more outside of the gym and take a few days off from going completely. I’ll start back midway through the week very lightly just focusing on quality basics. The last day of the week I’ll do some quality working sets at whatever weight I feel like working up to. I resume training normally the following week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I’m feeling okay with my training, but I need to give my body a break, I’ll just cut out my top sets for a week and potentially make my back-off/working sets lighter. This is just enough to keep yourself going through the motions, but giving your body a break from intensity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I’m feeling very physically drained, I’ll go into the gym each day and just hit basic working sets at a very light intensity (3x10 controlled tempo on all of the basics) and drill a lot of mobility and assistance work with resistance bands to finish up. This works well, but it can be much different from usual training especially if you’re advanced/intermediate, potentially getting you out of a groove. Sometimes though, this can be just what you need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is opinionated; these are training styles that I have worked through and seen others work through with good results. If you see ideas here that you want to take into your own training, feel free to. If you try this and see good results with it feel free to let me know. The same goes with results that are less than stellar. I’d love to hear feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestions for me (for writing, post style, or post content), I’d be incredibly happy to hear it. Feel free to email me at &lt;em&gt;matt -&amp;gt; mattgray dot net&lt;/em&gt; or leave a comment below. Thanks for reading :).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/fitness/2018/02/24/weighted-bodyweight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/fitness/2018/02/24/weighted-bodyweight.html</guid>
        
        <category>bodyweight</category>
        
        <category>powerlifting</category>
        
        <category>gymnastics</category>
        
        
        <category>fitness</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stopwatching 1.2.1 Update</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;First of all, if you’re interested in my Stopwatching application (a handsfree exercise/general task timer), there’s a link on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgray.net/projects.html&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; section of this site. It gives a quick blurb detailing what it’s about. Now that that’s over, here’s what I’ve updated in the application and my thoughts on the current state of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Countdown&lt;/strong&gt; - The main critical review of the application mentioned that the countdown beeps were practically inaudible, especially when music was playing. To alleviate this, I switched to a different method of playing audio and added beeps that play much louder, especially over music.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Landscape&lt;/strong&gt; - Along with this, the landscape mode in the app wasn’t very useful. To change this I made it so the app removed the list view when in landscape and enlarged the timer to take up a majority of the screen. A problem with this is that I no longer had the start and stop buttons on the screen when in landscape, so I made it so that tapping the timer label starts and pauses the timer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither of these changes were very major, I just wanted to release at least one more update for the app because I haven’t gotten the chance to do much swift programming over the past year of school. One other upside to updating is that the app now displays correctly on the iPhone X :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you have any other suggestions for the application, please feel free to leave a review on the app store or comment below (I’ll definitely see the latter quicker&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/development/2017/12/15/stopwatching-121-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/development/2017/12/15/stopwatching-121-update.html</guid>
        
        <category>bodyweight</category>
        
        <category>swift</category>
        
        <category>gymnastics</category>
        
        <category>stopwatching</category>
        
        
        <category>development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflecting on Four Years of Training Powerlifting and Gymnastics</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;intro-and-training-history&quot;&gt;Intro and Training History&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll begin with an overview of my successes, mistakes, and overall principles I have learned over the past four years. Following that I have included a brief and detailed training history that includes links to videos of the respective accomplishments. Feel free to read any or all parts of this post, I tried to section it up so that it’s digestible in pieces. This isn’t scientific or exact, it’s just a collection of thoughts and realizations I’ve had over these past four years and my experiences in training the multiple disciplines I choose to pursue. To be precise, the first year or so of training weren’t purposely focused on powerlifting or gymnastics, but I included elements of each from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could’ve made better progress on one discipline if I chose it exclusively, but would I have been as happy with my overall strength or overall mobility had I? The answer is a firm no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mistakes&quot;&gt;Mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the main mistakes I made in my training that I feel slowed down my gains in strength and mobility. If I could go back, I would make these changes in order to progress faster and have fewer injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Following a program consistently from the start&lt;/strong&gt; - No one knows what they’re doing in the beginning. Even with all the book and program knowledge in the world, you still don’t know your own body unless you have worked out before. I wish I had began with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VpobvFPR6hQ&quot;&gt;reddit recommended routine&lt;/a&gt; specifically. Had I followed that as well as stretched with purpose, my initial base moving into more advanced strength and flexibility work would have been much more solid. Don’t think you’re above doing progressions; even if you have the strength, your mobility or connective tissue may have not yet adapted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training with too much intensity&lt;/strong&gt; - Beginners can work for varying amounts of time (some a month, some for much longer) closer to failure and see great progression; they can beat their body up and then come back in two days, mostly recovered, and beat their body up again. After a while, this stops. The body starts to break down, progression slows, and sometimes begins to slide backwards. Being a large guy, this happened to me relatively quickly working on gymnastics strength. I worked to hard on press handstands and injured my wrists. I worked too hard on weighted dips and hurt my shoulders. I worked too hard on weighted chin-ups and hurt my elbows. I still fight the desire to work towards failure every time I’m in the gym. Adequate sub-maximal work drives progress.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not listening to your body when it hurts&lt;/strong&gt; - Pain is different than soreness. Off of the last bullet, there were too many times when my joints ached and I just wanted to do “1 more set.” Those 1 sets added up and gave me more overuse injuries than I would’ve liked to deal with. When your joints ache, if you don’t have access to a physical therapist, research what is causing the pain and do prehab/rehab work to get blood flow to the area so it can heal. Light weight, low intensity, high rep (30+) at a slow tempo. Every time I’ve had an injury, that has sped up the recovery from what would otherwise be more time spent wallowing about the pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;successes&quot;&gt;Successes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training consistently&lt;/strong&gt; - Over the past 4 years I’ve trained on average 5 days a week (3-4 strength workouts and 1-2 skill sessions/gymnastics practices). Even with some of those sessions lacking perfect programming, I kept working hard and consistently plugging away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training through injuries&lt;/strong&gt; - This does not mean pushing through pain on a specific exercise. Rehabbing the injured body part and working what is not injured is so important for getting through an injury, mentally and physically. When I hurt my wrists, I worked pulling, flexibility, and rehab. When I hurt my elbow, I worked legs and rehab. You just have to get through somehow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tracking&lt;/strong&gt; - I track my calories even when I don’t measure exactly what I eat. I track my workouts even when I don’t follow a perfect program. I think keeping some type of training history, whether vague or specific, is helpful to know whether or not what you’re doing is working. On top of that, when progress feels slow, it can be helpful to look back and know that you’re still moving forward, no matter how slow it may be.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keeping a balance&lt;/strong&gt; - Even though I train powerlifting I still work on my flexibility heavily, this could be said the other way around as well. Unless you’re competing at the elite level of a sport, having a balanced combination of strength, mobility, and athleticism makes for a much happier human in my experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overall-principles&quot;&gt;Overall Principle(s)?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Powerlifting with gymnastics&lt;/strong&gt; - Even if you’re competitive in one or both of these disciplines, unless it’s at an elite level, both have a good place in anyone’s training. Some upper body work through gymnastics is invaluable, while powerlifting is hard to replace in regards to the lower body. Read more on this subject &lt;a href=&quot;http://stevenlow.org/integrating-bodyweight-and-barbell-training/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s a marathon, not a sprint&lt;/strong&gt; - This saying is a cliche, but not without reason. If you want to be able to move well throughout your life, take things slow, &lt;em&gt;rarely&lt;/em&gt; max out, and do your damn mobility work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stretch with purpose&lt;/strong&gt; - When you stretch, do it with as much purpose as you do strength training. Find out what ranges you lack, relax into them, and &lt;em&gt;contract in the end ranges&lt;/em&gt; to build strength there. Use your own muscles to push/pull yourself deeper. The more strength you have in a range, the more willing your body will be to go there. Read more &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitlaughlin.wordpress.com/tag/contract-relax-approach/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on contract-relax stretching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effort&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep it sub-maximal&lt;/strong&gt;  Once you’re not a beginner anymore (squatting 1.5x bodyweight, deadlifting between 1.5 and 2x, benching your bodyweight, repping pull-ups and dips easily, etc), try to stick away from failure. By this I mean always try and have an extra rep in the tank at least, if not more. You will feel fresher in your workouts, you won’t be mad from failure,  and you will be more likely to not get injured. When working away from failure you can get in more volume which is what spurs strength gains and muscular growth.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put in your best effort&lt;/strong&gt; - This ties in closely with keeping it sub-maximal by not being afraid to push yourself. It’s a fine line to toe, because it’s easy to just go through easy motions at the gym, but you don’t want to wreck your body by doing maximal effort work. If you feel great one day, try for a personal best, but it certainly isn’t an event that should occur every workout or every week.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variety&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to switch things up&lt;/strong&gt; - If you have been grinding at something for a few months and it’s taking its physical or mental toll, don’t be afraid to give it a break. Whether it’s because you’re getting close to injury or you’re just tired of it, having variety is good.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you choose a goal, stick with it (have a routine!)&lt;/strong&gt; - On the other side of the spectrum, stick with your goals until you get them or at least make significant progress. Remaining consistent will yield results.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to play either&lt;/strong&gt; - This is similar to switching things up, but I mean it more on a small timescale. If you have the chance to try something you otherwise wouldn’t get to, don’t be afraid to ditch the routine for a day to try something new. If you’re consistent 9 times out of 10, or 99/100, then one little switch-up won’t destroy you, it may give a new perspective that will be helpful in the long-term :).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balance&lt;/strong&gt; - This is the last thing I can think of currently. No matter what, just think critically about your practice and balance your consistency with your play, hard effort with easier activities, mobility with strength, and training with life in general. The 80/20 rule (20% of the effort gives 80% of the results) is a great heuristic. Going beyond 20% effort will give you results you wouldn’t have thought possible over the long term, but sometimes it is important to relax. Great gains can be maintained easily (with a select few strength and mobility exercises) when other callings in life make themselves known.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;training-history&quot;&gt;Training History&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief&quot;&gt;Brief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 years ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight: 175lbs (down from 195lbs just from diet)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Squat: 150lbs for 5 reps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bench: n/a&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadlift: 225 for 5 reps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pull-ups: 3x4 bodyweight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dips: n/a&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No static holds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Handbalancing: scared to death&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexibility: barely touch toes, no pancake or splits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight: 211lbs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Squat: 335lbs for 6 reps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bench: 225lbs for 3 reps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadlift: 405lbs for 4 reps (trained after squats always)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pull-ups: +50lbs for 10 reps pronated, 160lb grip for 1 rep neutral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dips: +90lbs for 9 reps, 180lbs for 1 rep&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5s straddle front lever, 10s full back lever, 19s tuck planche, assisted iron cross holds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Handbalancing: 45s HS, straddle/tuck/pike up, press eccentrics, freestanding HSPU eccentrics, no german hang&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexibility: palms to floor cold pike, head to floor cold pancake (stomach to floor warmed up), left leg forwards front splits, middle splits 6” away from ground at center, german hang&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first year and a half I followed a haphazard linear progression with a completely nonsensical split that eventually became an organized PPL routine. Following this, I did about half a year of linear progression (full body, 3x a week) while adjusting to gymnastics-oriented training and college. For a year and 3/4 after this (3.75 years in) I followed DUP. At first (first 3 months or so) I was training to intensely and plateaued in upper body strength. Saw great gains after that initial plateau. For the past 3-4 months I’ve followed a bent-arm/straight-arm split while powerlifting for lower body 2 times per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;detailed&quot;&gt;Detailed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-overcoming-gravity&quot;&gt;Before Overcoming Gravity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2013 (4 years ago)&lt;/strong&gt; - I began with running on a treadmill and doing the some of the most basic bro-exercises in the gym. My goal was to simply run a mile as fast as the treadmill could go. While I don’t have my old running notes, I reached this within about 6 months by the late spring/early summer of 2014 and that was a 5:20 mile on the treadmill where there was no air resistance. By this point I had cut down from about 196lbs to 166lbs through some split I dreamed up, a decent diet, and running. I was also training for high school baseball primarily at this point. I was also able to do maybe 3-5 bodyweight pull-ups and 1 or 2 dips.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 2014&lt;/strong&gt; - My baseball coach at this point introduced me to the concept of push/pull/legs split. At this point I worked out 3 times/week and hit each muscle group once. I did this workout and started to get better at squatting (maybe 150lbs for 3x5), dumbbell bench (60lbs for 3x5) (no barbell because it was rumored to be bad for baseball players), and doing pull-ups (could maybe do 5-8 around now?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2014 (3 years ago)&lt;/strong&gt; - Around a year in was when I started to have a respectable physique. I moved into push/pull/legs 6 days/week around this point, my squat was moving up to moderate weights of 225lbs for reps, and I began to train weighted pull-ups and muscle ups because they looked cool.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 2015&lt;/strong&gt; - I was starting to get really confident with my strength and pitching abilities in baseball, but I overtrained hard. Weighted pull-ups and muscle-ups took their toll on my elbow with pitching, and one day I didn’t warm-up enough on the mound and I started to get severe tendinitis that day. I couldn’t lift curl my right arm (elbow flexion) much more than 20 degrees for a few days. This knocked me out of baseball for good (throwing still aggravates my elbow) and out of upper body work for a month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 2015&lt;/strong&gt; - I began training for track in February (1600m and 3200m) to do some sport during my last semester of high school. To keep a long story short, I got my mile time down to about 5:42 from 6:30 and my body-fat to about the lowest it ever has been. I started training my upper body again with weighted pull-ups. This was also around when I started deadlifting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-overcoming-gravity&quot;&gt;After Overcoming Gravity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 2015&lt;/strong&gt; - This was the major shift that made my training purposeful. I read the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgray.net/books/2017/07/03/overcoming-gravity-2.html&quot;&gt;Overcoming Gravity&lt;/a&gt;. From this, I learned (and am still realizing) a large deal about programming for strength as well as the long-term goals I would like to achieve. This was when I started seriously pursuing bodyweight strength along with powerlifting for the lower body. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iYsK1ZvpylU&quot;&gt;I also got my first rings muscle-up.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 2015&lt;/strong&gt; - Before coming to college, I was just beginning to work on wall handstands, I had achieved a bar and ring muscle-up, and I could do weighted chins with 70lbs for 3x5. Starting college I was 173lbs just about and very lean. On the unlimited meal plan I decided to start bulking up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2015 (2 years ago)&lt;/strong&gt; - Here was where I started making decent progress on accomplishing some intermediate bodyweight goals. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NCGBqWq3liE&quot;&gt;I held my first few handstands over the past few months&lt;/a&gt;, I achieved a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sjwd8BXMFeA&quot;&gt;half-bodyweight added chin-up&lt;/a&gt;, and my flexibility began to improve. I was also up to about 183lbs. My squat hit 315lbs around here and my deadlift was about 315lbs for 5 reps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 2016&lt;/strong&gt; - I began to improve further after a slight plateau in strength. My weighted chins and weighted dips were at half-bodyweight for 5 reps around here. I started to get full back-levers and solid advanced-tuck front-levers. My handstands were now about 10% consistent instead of less than 5%. My good split and pancake were starting to get down to the floor. I began training the press-handstand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 2016&lt;/strong&gt; - I started to train the iron-cross this summer as well as improve on my press. I injured my wrist around this time though and that took me out of a lot of handbalancing and pushing work for three months. It was wrist-extensor tendinitis. I was squatting around 285 for 5 here and deadlifting around 365 for 5. My powerlifting progress was always on the lacking side.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2016 (1 year ago)&lt;/strong&gt; - From August until now I worked on leg and pulling strength primarily while my wrist healed. My front lever began greatly improving as well as my squat and deadlift. I squatted 315 for 6 and deadlifted 405 for 5. My wrist was healed by now so I started to work on pushing more, specifically with my handstands.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 2017&lt;/strong&gt; - Got my weighted chins and dips up to 140x1 and 135x3 respectively. Also achieved straddle front lever.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 2017&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W3GoyN-mOIw&amp;amp;t=50s&quot;&gt;Hit my highest weighted chin and weighted dip ever (160lbs and 180lbs respectively). Also hit a really ugly 315x11 squat PR (this was when I decided my form needed fixing badly).&lt;/a&gt; I deloaded heavily and worked on keeping my knees out as well as preventing my hips from rising too early. The latter of which I still struggle with somewhat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 2017&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7G3VFrVNIt8&quot;&gt;Competed at my first national club gymnastics competition&lt;/a&gt;. My rings routine was: Kip support &amp;gt; Forward roll to support &amp;gt; Press shoulderstand &amp;gt; Down to hang, muscle-up &amp;gt; Down to hang, back lever &amp;gt; Cast, Swing, Fly-away&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 2017&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lfazi8uI4hQ&quot;&gt;Achieved my first press-handstand. Injured other wrist within a few weeks (progression video here).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 2017&lt;/strong&gt; - Did a 3 month block of coaching with the author of Overcoming Gravity. Focused mostly on building time in statics and improving work capacity. Saw incredible gains following DUP (followed from January until August). No major skill gains, just hold time improvement and weight moved improvement. Comfortable with cross eccentrics on low rings by now. Achieved rings press handstand with cable support at top.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 2017&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tQRAXAVtjNA&quot;&gt;Achieved a 405lb low-bar back-squat and a straddle front-lever row in the same training session. Two major training goals.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2017&lt;/strong&gt; - Wrist has healed. Training for a powerlifting meet in January. Have reached the aforementioned current-day numbers on all lifts. After the meet I’d like to cut weight, maintain my lower-body powerlifting numbers, and improve my flexibility and upper body gymnastics strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments/questions/critiques, feel free to comment them here. I would absolutely love to hear them. I hope some of this information is useful in applying it to your training :).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 01:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/fitness/2017/11/18/reflecting-on-four-years-of-training.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/fitness/2017/11/18/reflecting-on-four-years-of-training.html</guid>
        
        <category>bodyweight</category>
        
        <category>powerlifting</category>
        
        <category>gymnastics</category>
        
        
        <category>fitness</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Intermediate and Advanced Gymnastics Strength Training</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few people on instagram and youtube have requested me to make a video covering my training program that I use. Haven’t had time to make the video yet and I wanted to go ahead and get it out in written form so I will go over the general plan here which you can apply to your own training and I will also cover how I use it myself. I originally made this routine using information I learned through reading Overcoming Gravity, and polished it by consulting with the book’s author, Steven Low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is focused on progression for intermediate gymnastics strength trainees who are on the larger side (&amp;gt;180lbs, &amp;gt;6’). Those are not hard limits, but the further you are below them, I’d only say this would be helpful if you were closer to the advanced/elite skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will first preface by saying that I am not a licensed personal trainer, nor am I a medical professional, so by using my program or any program for that matter you are doing so at your own risk. This program is for an intermediate to advanced trainee, and you should have a good idea of your own limitations when using this. If you’re not intermediate/advanced in reference to the bodyweight charts made by Steven Low for Overcoming Gravity, then you should use a more beginner-focused program because this program will not efficiently make you stronger. I’ll start with the general structure of the program and follow up with how I implement it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Meta&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most bodyweight training routines can be divided into warm-up, skill work, strength work, accessory work, and cool down. I will not cover warm-up here, I do a general warm-up routine involving upper body warm-up, core body positioning drills, lower body mobility, and foam rolling if something in particular feels tight. Skill work follows and can be between 15-30 minutes of practice on a skill that isn’t as dependent on strength as it is on becoming familiar with the movement pattern (hand balancing, rings work, floor work, etc). Again, this is primarily for intermediate trainees, so you should already have that part of your workout down along with your understanding of why basic aspects of a balanced workout are the way they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the strength routine, I’ll start with the general layout. Legs training will be left up to one’s self. I personally use 5/3/1 for leg progression and program accessory work by feel, because leg work simply is not as important to me. 5/3/1 with accessory work consisting of 3x8-10 of squats and 3x8-10 deadlifts has been enough to get me to a 1.8x bodyweight squat and a 2.4x bodyweight deadlift at 6’2” 211lbs bodyweight. Due to work and school, I usually do legs whenever I have the time. Some weeks I’ll have two leg days, and some weeks both squats and deadlifts will be done with an upper body workout. It all depends on scheduling. I’d recommend leg work on different days so that one can focus on it and upper body as well, but do what time permits. Again, leg strength is not the primary focus of this program, so on to upper body work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;programming-the-meat&quot;&gt;Programming (The Meat)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generalized&quot;&gt;Generalized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to progression, periodization, set&amp;amp;rep scheme, and overall training philosophy. For upper body, I use a Daily Undulating Periodization or DUP scheme to progress my strength. I’ll link to an article in the description about it, but in short, DUP involves cycling through all or most repetition/intensity ranges over the course of a microcycle which is usually one training week, instead of over the course of a mesocycle which is usually 4-6 weeks in the case of traditional periodization. In this program I stick to a light, medium, and heavy upper body day.  Each day is within the 10-15, 5-10, and 3-5 rep range respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stick with 3 pairs of exercises each with 3 to 6 sets. The first pair are my primary pushing and pulling goals, while the second pair are secondary pushing and pulling goals. I use the third pair of exercises to supplement whatever aspects of pushing and pulling I may be deficient in, whether certain planes of movement or specific exercises. Holds I usually keep between 4 and 10s, any more doesn’t have a great carry-over to strength for me personally and any less doesn’t accumulate enough volume. Negatives I usually keep between 7 and 10s for the same reasons. Dynamics (exercises doing a full concentric and eccentric) are what I focus the DUP work on in the aforementioned rep ranges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varying holds and negatives in the style of DUP work for me to a small extent, it didn’t give me enough of a training stimulus at what I was working on when I tried to keep everything strictly following a DUP style. I personally found the best results focusing all of my static hold efforts on the same variation throughout the week (4x8-10s tuck planche holds for example) except for the heavy day where I would do 5-8 sets of 3-5s holds. More sets for shorter timed holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progression is done by adding weight, increasing repetitions, increasing sets, increasing hold quality, or slowing tempo of dynamic exercises. One of the most important things I can’t stress enough is to never sacrifice form or quality for progression. If you’re not progressing without major loss of form, you may need to think about your recovery, volume of work, exercise selection, progression selection, or other training factors. I always try and progress weekly in some regard (because DUP repeats on a weekly cycle), but if I can’t, firstly I’ll work on my recovery and secondly I’ll reconsider my training if a stagnating or negative trend continues for longer than two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessory work is entirely dependent on the person, I like to always keep some elbow, shoulder, and wrist prehab included, because it what works for me to keep my upper body moving smoothly, so take this as you may.  I like to keep my upper body prehab consisting of high rep controlled tempo bicep curls (think 50+ reps), similarly high rep/controlled tempo wrist curls and extensions, and external rotation prehab in the form of face pulls for 15-20 reps. 2-3 sets does the trick. Reverse wrist push-ups have treated my wrists well too (reverse in regards to the back of the hands being on the ground, not the palms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-specific-program&quot;&gt;My Specific Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgray.net/assets/routine.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://mattgray.net/assets/routine.png&quot; alt=&quot;My routine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a spreadsheet of my program. I implement the exact principles I was talking about above working to achieve the iron cross, straddle planche, front lever, and handstand push-up on the rings. I focus on my main goals first, follow with my secondary goals, and then finish with basic strength movements because I’ve had much better results including them compared to excluding them. My leg day is currently focusing on strength in regards to mobility because that’s what’s important to me right now. I may do deadlifts and squats for higher reps occasionally on Friday, but it’s not a main focus of mine right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing about the rationale would be redundant, but if you have any questions on my specifics, ask below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-my-program-has-taken-me&quot;&gt;Where My Program has Taken Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my numbers I can find since I began using this scheme at the start of the 2017. I’ve also had to deal with sickness and injury a good few times (because of not warming up, stretching, or doing my prehab sometimes when I ran really low on time due to my life schedule and lacking recovery, also because of my schedule).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;planche 10s tuck &amp;gt; 20s tuck as well as first advanced tuck&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;front lever 2s straddle &amp;gt; 6s straddle (and much cleaner adv tuck)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;weighted dips 135x1 &amp;gt; 180x1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;weighted chins 130x1 &amp;gt; 160x1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iron cross no negative control and no assisted crosses &amp;gt; clean negative control and 3/4 4s bodyweight crosses (estimated band resistance?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;deadlift 405x5 &amp;gt; 455x4, no max &amp;gt; 500x1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;squat 325x5 &amp;gt; 325x9, 355x1 &amp;gt; 385x1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applying-to-powerlifting&quot;&gt;Applying to Powerlifting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this program while making gains with powerlifting, I would program leg work separately, adding a third day if you desire, and simply add in bench press a one of your upper body pushing exercises during the week.  For example, you could switch out bench and planche holds (or push-ups and keep the planche work in), strict press for handstand-push-up work. Whatever your priorities are, you have to program in that order. I prefer the most technically complex (planche and iron cross) exercises first, but you can also prioritize by importance. If you’re having difficulty prioritizing, you may need to cut down on the number of your goals. There’s plenty of time to tackle different activities, so it’s okay to put some on the back-burner for a while, as long as you keep your mobility in shape, they’ll be there waiting when you get back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess I would like to add a slight philosophical note too. When you start getting to an intermediate/advanced point in your training, progress can start slowing down. Don’t let it bother you. Try and take a step back from your training to get some enjoyment out of it. If you’re not training for competition, take some time off occasionally from your main training and take a week or two to focus on the basics as well as prehab if you’ve had a few injuries. Don’t neglect flexibility. I didn’t talk about it much here, because there are much better resources online about it, but I included it in my personal program. Flexibility helps greatly, not just in bodyweight fitness, but in everyday life. Don’t skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first time writing longer form and I did it in a lot of different sittings so I’ll gladly take any critiques as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, feel free to ask below, but please go back to the beginning if you were skipping around before you have questions. While there are different sections, some information refers to things previously mentioned. I hope this helps, train hard and smart :).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/fitness/2017/07/27/intermediate-advanced-gymnastics-strength.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/fitness/2017/07/27/intermediate-advanced-gymnastics-strength.html</guid>
        
        <category>bodyweight</category>
        
        <category>powerlifting</category>
        
        <category>gymnastics</category>
        
        
        <category>fitness</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Overcoming Gravity (2nd Edition)</title>
        <description>&lt;span class=&quot;booktitle&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stevenlow.org/book/&quot;&gt;Overcoming Gravity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; - As many others have said, this book is the bible of bodyweight and gymnastics strength training. From goal setting, exercise selection, routine creation, and periodization, this book provides information on how beginning, intermediate, and advanced trainees can implement these concepts. I've structured my upper-body training for the past year and a half on what I have learned (and continue to learn from the 2nd edition) from this wonderful book; I recommend it to anyone interested in athletic training. As said by the quote on the back of the 1st edition, &quot;Lack of activity destroys the good condition of every human being, while movement and methodical physical exercise save it and preserve it.&quot; -Plato
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 11:42:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/books/2017/07/03/overcoming-gravity-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/books/2017/07/03/overcoming-gravity-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>books</category>
        
        <category>fitness</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Earth Abides</title>
        <description>&lt;span class=&quot;booktitle&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earth_Abides&quot;&gt;Earth Abides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by George R. Stewart - I don't hesitate to rank &lt;span class=&quot;booktitle&quot;&gt;Earth Abides&lt;/span&gt; as my all-time favorite fiction book. To not give anything away I'll keep this as short as possible. On the surface this book is incredibly different from the life that most will live (assuming we don't run into a post-apocalyptic situation in the next century), however I feel the general arc of the protagonist's story is a sad yet beautiful way to look at life. It gave me a new perspective on living and what I can accomplish with my years on Earth.
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 11:42:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://mattgray.net/books/2017/07/03/earth-abides.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mattgray.net/books/2017/07/03/earth-abides.html</guid>
        
        <category>books</category>
        
        <category>fiction</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
